<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Charity recommended, in a sermon preached at the assizes held at Norwich, upon Thursday the 29th of July, 1686 by John Turner ...</title>
            <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63904</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3304</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5344</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11962849</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11962849</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51617</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63904)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51617)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 519:48)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Charity recommended, in a sermon preached at the assizes held at Norwich, upon Thursday the 29th of July, 1686 by John Turner ...</title>
                  <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 33 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills Junior, for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John XIII, 35 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Charity --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51617:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> CHARITY RECOMMENDED, IN A SERMON Preached at the ASSIZES HELD AT NORWICH, Upon <hi>Thurſday</hi> the 29th of <hi>July,</hi> 1686.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNER</hi> Hoſpitaller of St. <hi>Thomas Southwark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now made Publick at the requeſt of the Gentlemen that heard it.</p>
            <p>Simmias Rhodius, <hi>de Amore Divino. Cui cuncta obtemperant, &amp; ab eodem originem ſui arceſſunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills</hi> Junior, for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the <hi>Biſhops-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls Church-yard,</hi> 1686.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51617:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51617:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Worſhipful, Sir</hi> Robert Nightingale, <hi>High-Sheriff of the County of</hi> Norfolk.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Am very ſenſible, it is too great an Honor that is done me by the general Approbation, which this Sermon met with; not that out of Real, or which is ſtill worſe, out of a Counterfeit and Pretended Modeſty, I would put an Affront upon ſo great an Audience, by ſeeming to ſuſpect the Judgments of ſo many excellent Perſons; but the Subject being <hi>Charity,</hi> was it ſelf a natural Preſervative againſt Cenſure; and that very word ſo often repeated to any Man that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands and feels the Senſe of it in himſelf, as every good Man unqueſtionably doth, hath an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible Charm belonging to it, ſo as together with its Name, to inſinuate its kindly and propitious Nature into every Breaſt, and with an Eloquence peculiar to it ſelf, to bribe even Cenſure and Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſm themſelves into a favourable Opinion of the Speaker. However, it is enough for me, though I had no other reaſon, that you, who have ſo great
<pb facs="tcp:51617:3"/> a right to diſpoſe of me as you pleaſe, have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded me to Publiſh what I Preach'd; and though I know very well, your Friendſhip is too great to let you judge otherwiſe, than too too kindly of any Performance of mine; yet I have no power to do any thing but obey, though it be to my own diſadvantage: Only, I confeſs, I am not a little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd, that ſo mean, and as you know, ſo tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary a Diſcourſe, being written in very great haſt, when I had ſcarce time to turn my ſelf, ſhould open ſo Glorious and Magnificent an Aſſize: But as it is, the World is welcome to it, and I have nothing further to ſay, but that it is very much in my Nature to wiſh and pray, that ſuch a Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Spirit as I have recommended, might uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally obtain, that I am very much in earneſt in what I have written, and that I hope that will attone ſomewhat for other defects.</p>
            <p>May you live as long, and as happily as you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve; and may the King never want ſuch Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and Obliging Miniſters in every Station, to diſperſe the happy Influences of his Government over a ſatisfied and contented People.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am, Sir,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Affectionate, Humble, and for ever moſt Oblig'd Servant,</hi> JOHN T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51617:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>JOHN XIII. 35.</bibl>
               <q>By this ſhall all men know that ye are my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, if ye have love one to another.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHen God had determin'd with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to exert that wondrous act of his omnipotent Will, by which this Univerſe was created out of nothing; the next thing he did was to conſult the Eternal <hi>Ideas</hi> of his own infinitely large and comprehenſive Mind, and by that excellent Platform which he found within himſelf, to reduce the univerſal Rubbiſh into a regular and comely Frame and ſuch as might at once declare, not only the Wiſdom, but alſo the Peace, the Equability, and the Conſtancy of his Nature. For in a Mind harras'd and diſcompoſed by troubleſome and anxious thoughts ruffled and diſtemper'd by inſatiable appetites, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally impotent deſires; a Mind that hath no govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, no maſtery of it ſelf, it is impoſſible there ſhould be a true and adequate comprehenſion of things, any more than a man in a Feaver can be wiſe, or play the <hi>Stoique</hi> in the midſt of the moſt exquiſite and ingenious Torments. And therefore the Poets, when they go about to deſcribe the happineſs and ſerenity of the Divine Nature, which is unqueſtionably <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipreſent,</hi> have yet notwithſtanding <hi>Mythologically</hi> confined it to thoſe peaceful Regions above this troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſom and noiſy <hi>Atmoſphere,</hi> where Storms and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51617:4"/> are deny'd to enter, where a profound Silence and unſhaken Calm makes ſelf-enjoyment eaſie and delightful. So <hi>Homer</hi> deſcribes his poetical <hi>Olympus</hi> the ſuppoſed Habitation of the Immortal Gods.</p>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
            <l>Heaven the ſweet place where happy Gods reſide,</l>
            <l>And where Peace flows with an Eternal Tide;</l>
            <l>There no fierce Winds diſturb the troubled Aire,</l>
            <l>No Rains deſcend, no threatning Clouds appeal,</l>
            <l>Nor Hail, nor Snow, nor pinching Froſts are ſeen,</l>
            <l>But all is warm and ſilent and ſerene.</l>
            <p>That Power of God by which he made the <hi>Chaos,</hi> and call'd it out of nothing into a dark, horrid and unhewn Exiſtence, is apt only to fill us with aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment and wonder; it preſents us only with the <hi>terrours of the Lord,</hi> and fills our minds naturally with diſmal apprehenſions, not knowing what uſe he may make of ſo exorbitant a Power as this, till his Goodneſs comes in to ſuccour and relieve us in the midſt of this black and dreadful contemplation; as the Angels themſelves, when they at firſt beheld ſuch an unweildy Maſs of indigeſted Matter, without any uſe, diſtinction or contrivance, were ſilent with aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment and poſſeſt with fear, expecting ſome dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and deſtructive Iſſue of ſuch an ill-bodeing, unpleaſant, and deform'd Beginning: But when they ſaw this confuſion by the divine Architect reduced into ſuch admirable and perfect Order, which gave them ſo firm and irrafragable demonſtration, of the wiſdom, the peace, and ſerenity of their Maker, then <hi>the morning ſtars</hi> imediately <hi>ſang-together, and all the Sons of God ſhouted for joy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51617:4"/>
            <p> Neither are we only inſtructed as well in the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as in the Peace and Tranquillity of the Divine Nature, which is immoveably bleſſed and happy in it ſelf, from the Harmony and <hi>ſymmetry</hi> of the ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble creation, which argues undeniably a Mind that is perfectly at leaſure and at eaſe, and free from all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of tumult and diſorder: But when we reflect upon the <hi>Animal</hi> World, upon the ſeveral orders and degrees of Beings, that are endued with a <hi>ſpecifick</hi> life, agreeable and ſuitable to the reſpective ends for which they were deſigned, furniſht with <hi>organs</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitely fitted for their ſupport and comfortable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment, and with Proviſions every were flowing round about them, and inviting them to refreſh, <hi>exhilarate</hi> and enjoy themſelves in the beſt manner their Natures will allow: When for our ſelves we find provided ready to our hands, not only a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petence of Meat, Drink and Raiment, barely to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the neceſſities of Life; not only a large Train of innocent and lawful pleaſures that attends all our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and wearies out even ſelf-denial it ſelf, with a perpetual and reſtleſs invitation; but alſo a ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and magnificent <hi>Theatre,</hi> ready prepared and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht for our Entertainment, a <hi>Scene</hi> of things wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of a reaſonable Soul, fitted for the noble and exalted <hi>operations</hi> of a contemplative and active mind, that leads us thorough ſenſible apartments into the preſence of the inviſible God, and by acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us firſt with his Exiſtence, brings us by gentle ſteps to the ſtudy of his Nature, and to the imitation and enjoyment of it.</p>
            <p>I ſay, when we reflect conſiderately and duly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe things, we are then plainly and certainly convinced, not only that God is, and that he is a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51617:5"/> at reſt within himſelf, that there are no Storms, no Billows in his Notion, no Troubles or Anxieties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to his <hi>Idea;</hi> but alſo in the language of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> that <hi>his mercy is over all his works,</hi> and that the <hi>Emanations</hi> of that mercy upon his Creatures in proportion to their reſpective capacity to be the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of it, are every whit as kind and gracious with reſpect to them, as the <hi>reflex</hi> acts of his own eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal mind, the ſenſe and ſelf-enjoyment of his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Nature, are kind and <hi>propitious</hi> and happy to himſelf.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, when we conſider attentively with our ſelves, that theſe things are not thus peradventure, or by chance, or at certain times and ſeaſons, like the Ebbing and Flowing of the Sea, or the encreaſe and waining of the Moon, as it were ſome <hi>lucid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervals</hi> of the Divine goodneſs, ſome certain fits of mercy and compaſſion, which have rather the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of infirmity than perfection; but that they are all of them regular and conſtant, and that his Providence goes on in an uninterrupted courſe thorough all Times and Ages, to let us know and feel, that <hi>his mercy is everlaſting, and that his truth endur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from generation to generation;</hi> from hence we learn, that his goodneſs is every whit as ſteady and as conſtant, as it is diffuſive and large, that in <hi>the Ancient of days,</hi> there is no viciſſitude, no decay of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but <hi>that he is the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever, in whom is no variableneſs, neither ſhadow of turning;</hi> that he is not a being of <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Will and Power, but that Goodneſs is rooted and riveted in his Nature, and that it is altogether inſeparable from it; nay, that it is his <hi>Eſſence,</hi> his very Life and Being, according to that expreſſion of St. <hi>John,</hi> that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51617:5"/> 
               <hi>God is love, he that loveth not,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>knoweth not God, for God is love.</hi> He is not <hi>Arbitrary,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determind's power, indifferent either to cruelty or mercy, unaccountable to himſelf as well as to his Creatures. He is not giddy humour, or alterable fancy, or wavering and uncertain caprice, but though he be infinite in himſelf, yet he hath mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Action, and Governs himſelf in all things by eternal Rules, from which he can no more <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varicate</hi> or flinch, than he can ceaſe to be himſelf, or bid a long farewell to all his Brightneſs, Bleſſedneſs and Perfection. He is Mercy, he is Kindneſs, he is all over Love, he is at once the moſt lovely, and the moſt loving Nature, and with an equal ſtream of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver failing Goodneſs, he waters his Creatures, and enjoys Himſelf, <hi>O God who is like unto thee, gracious and merciful, long ſuffering and plenteous in goodneſs and truth; as the Hart panteth after the water brooks, ſo panteth my Soul after thee, O God,</hi> the Fountain of Pleaſure, the everſpringing Well of <hi>Living waters,</hi> and the Eternal ſource of inexhauſtible Mercy.</p>
            <p>There are two things required to the happineſs of any being whatſoever, the firſt is an indolency and tranquillity, a calm and quiet ſenſe within it ſelf, not diſcompoſed by turbulent and uneaſie paſſions, nor toſt too and fro without any conduct or ſteerage of it ſelf, by infinite and uncertain deſires. The Second is, that every thing without, have ſo far at leaſt a <hi>Congruity,</hi> harmony and agreement with it, that nothing may diſturb or ſhake this inward ſenſe. So that the whole being with relation to it ſelf, and with reſpect to objects that are external to it, is to be like a ſmooth Sea upon a ſtill and ſilent Evening, where <hi>Tritons</hi> dance, and <hi>Dolphins</hi> play,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51617:6"/> and <hi>Sirens</hi> all around rejoyce and Sing, and all the <hi>Sea Nymphs</hi> revel and careſs each other upon the gladſome ſurface of the <hi>great Abyſſe,</hi> which drinks in nothing but light and peace from without, and is ſurrounded by nothing but a ſerene and <hi>Azure</hi> Sky.</p>
            <p>But wherever there is an averſion or <hi>antipathy</hi> of one Being to another, whether it proceed out of fickleneſs, uncertainty, and viciſſitude of Nature, or out of fear, or out of ſome peculiar and unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable hatred, which it cannot exempt or deliver it ſelf from, the firſt of theſe argues ſo great a want of Judgment, which proceeds upon immutable and certain reaſons, the Second ſo great weakneſs and infirmity, and the Third is in it ſelf ſo troubleſome and tormenting wherever it is found, that all theſe are perfectly inconſiſtent with the happyneſs of any Being, and therefore muſt not be aſcribed to God, who is <hi>infinitely wiſe,</hi> and therefore cannot be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as to his judgment of things, and <hi>infinitely pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful,</hi> ſo that he need not fear any croſs or dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous event, and who muſt be <hi>happy</hi> if any ſuch thing there be, becauſe <hi>all perfection</hi> is contained in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and <hi>happyneſs</hi> without queſtion is the beſt Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment that can belong to any Being whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; it is that without which Exiſtence it ſelf would be a burthen, and all other attributes whatſoever they are, even Power, Wiſdom, Juſtice, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs themſelves, would be but a rack and torment to the Poſſeſſor. And <hi>who can dwell with Everlaſting burnings?</hi> What Being could be ſo miſerable as the <hi>Supream</hi> and <hi>ſelf-exiſtent,</hi> if any <hi>faſtidious</hi> averſion or diſlike, any <hi>deſperate</hi> animoſity or <hi>inconciliable</hi> hatred, which in ſo <hi>great</hi> a Mind muſt be propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd to it, had the power Eternally to diſturb him?</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:51617:6"/>
            <p> It is true indeed, that in Scripture we find a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent mention of his <hi>wrath,</hi> his <hi>indignation,</hi> his <hi>fierce anger,</hi> and his <hi>ſore diſpleaſure,</hi> and his <hi>jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie that burns like fire,</hi> and the like; but yet theſe things do not argue him to be of a <hi>paſſible</hi> Nature, but only firſt, they refer to thoſe puniſhments of our ſins which in the courſe of his Providence are inflicted upon us, or which are denounced againſt us by ſuch expreſſions as theſe, in caſe we do not Repent, and according to the proportion, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or leſſer weight and heavineſs of theſe Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; ſo in an humane way of ſpeaking we ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is uſually ſo in caſes of revenge and animoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty among Men, that he is <hi>more</hi> or <hi>leſs</hi> angry or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed, not that he is <hi>more</hi> or <hi>leſs</hi> happy than he was before, or that any impreſſions can be made upon him, that can unſettle or diſcompoſe the equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of his mind, but only he beholds every fooliſh and unreaſonable Action, which is the very nature and notion of all Sin, with an <hi>impaſſible</hi> contempt, and with a diſlike that hath no other effect upon him, but only to move him upon reaſons of Juſtice, to Puniſh the Offence as it deſerves, for the Good of the World, and for an Example to others.</p>
            <p>Very frequently in our own perſons he Chaſtiſeth us ſo lightly, that it is plain he deſires our amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not our deſtruction; but when the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is never ſo ſevere, yet ſtill there is a gracious meaning and intention in it, for the good of the Univerſe, which is infinitely more precious to him than the ſafety of any ſingle perſon whatſoever, that other People warned by our Example <hi>may hear and fear, and do no more ſo wickedly.</hi> So that his <hi>Anger</hi> is indeed but an effect of his <hi>Love,</hi> and that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51617:7"/> which we call his <hi>Wrath</hi> and his <hi>Iudignation,</hi> is in truth nothing elſe but a particular and diſtinct branch of his <hi>infinite</hi> and <hi>incomprehenſible Mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or Secondly, when ſuch things as theſe are ſpoken of him in Scripture, they are to be referred to the <hi>purity</hi> of his Nature, to which all ſin hath the <hi>greateſt incongruity</hi> that any two things can have to one another; not that there ariſeth any painful or tormenting ſenſe, to trouble or diſquiet his enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of himſelf, but only according to an humane way of ſpeaking, the <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> in this caſe aſcribes thoſe paſſions to God, which good Men upon the like occaſion experience in themſelves, when they ſee his Divinity Blaſphemed, his Altars Profaned, his Churches Sacrilegiouſly rob'd and ſpoil'd, his Prieſthood perſecuted or neglected, his Laws diſappointed and fruſtrated by <hi>Enthuſiaſm,</hi> or by open Wickedneſs affronted, his Religion and his Honor trampled under foot, either by <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Hereſie</hi> on the one hand, or by <hi>Licentiouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Lewdneſs</hi> on the other: And to this purpoſe there are two things very remarkable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That though the Scripture be ſometimes very fierce in the Denunciation of Gods Anger againſt Sin, yet it frequently <hi>dilutes</hi> and <hi>blends</hi> thoſe ſharp expreſſions with kind and gracious aſſurances of his Love, and tells us plainly, that it is this alone which is <hi>truly</hi> agreeable and ſuitable to his Nature; but that the other, that is, his Anger, or that which in the adminiſtration of his providence hath the <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> ſemblance and appearance of it, is a thing which is put upon him by the neceſſities of Juſtice, and that he finds no other <hi>Complacency</hi> or ſatisfaction in the Puniſhments he inflicts, but what ariſes from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51617:7"/> the <hi>inward</hi> ſenſe and conſciouſneſs of thoſe <hi>gracious</hi> ends for which thoſe <hi>unwilling</hi> ſeverities are deſigned.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is to be obſerved, that God in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is not always repreſented, as <hi>Angry</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed at ſin, but ſometimes as <hi>laughing</hi> at it, and treating it with contempt and ſcorn: and indeed, both of theſe are aſcribed together to him in that <hi>Prophetick</hi> rapture of <hi>David,</hi> in the ſecond Pſalm, <hi>Why do the Heathen rage? And the people imagin a vain thing? the Kings of the Earth ſet themſelves and the Rulers take council together againſt the Lord and againſt his Anointed, ſaying, let us break their bands aſunder and caſt away their cords from us, he that ſitteth in the Heavens ſhall laugh, the Lord ſhall have them in deriſion, then ſhall he ſpeak unto them in his wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure,</hi> not that theſe two paſſions are indeed <hi>conſiſtent</hi> or <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petible</hi> together at one and the ſame time, they being <hi>directly</hi> oppoſite and contrary to each other, nor that God whoſe Nature is perfectly <hi>impaſſible,</hi> is really capable of <hi>either</hi> of theſe habits or diſpoſitions of mind. But by the <hi>later</hi> of theſe was ſignified that juſt and <hi>condign</hi> Puniſhment that was in the full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of time to overtake thoſe Kings and Nations that were Enemies to the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and oppoſed <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> by bitter Perſecutions, notwithſtanding all the innocence and the reaſon of its Principles, and notwithſtanding all that <hi>ſupernatural</hi> Evidence of Signs and Miracles, and extraordinary Gifts by which it received its confirmation from above, and by the Firſt of them, by Gods <hi>Laughing</hi> and <hi>Scorning</hi> at the vain deſigns of Men that reject the offers of his Grace, and endeavor to no purpoſe to reverſe his immutable Decrees, is meant, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51617:8"/> his happineſs cannot be injur'd or impair'd by any attempt of ours, that he is not to be diſappointed in his intentions or deſigns by any humane Policy or Strength, that he deſpiſes, diſregards and perfectly ſets at nought ſuch vain imaginations of the Sons of Men, that his Nature is <hi>impaſſible, inacceſſible, irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtible,</hi> that when he ſtretches out his <hi>mighty Arm,</hi> it is not an <hi>Arm of Fleſh</hi> that can oppoſe it, and that he is no otherwiſe concerned at the wickedneſs of Men, than only to puniſh and reſtrain it by his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and by the Eternal meaſures of his Power and Juſtice.</p>
            <p>And thus I have ſhewn more largely than I intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, what the <hi>Nature</hi> of God is, that he is a <hi>Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> and <hi>Gracious</hi> Being, <hi>ſlow to Anger</hi> and <hi>of great Pity,</hi> that he delights not in Puniſhment, and that <hi>in the midſt of Judgment he remembers Mercy,</hi> that the <hi>Emanations</hi> of his Goodneſs are truly Natural and <hi>Congenerous</hi> to him, but that his Judgments are only <hi>Secondary</hi> things, things that are not inflicted for themſelves, but for ends of Mercy and Compaſſion, for amendment and example, for preſerving the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the World, from moldring into Anarchy and Confuſion, and keeping it from falling foul up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ſelf; and this though it may be ſufficient to have ſhewn by the plain Inſtances already produced, yet there is a <hi>greater</hi> inſtance than all this yet behind, and that is his ſending his <hi>Son</hi> into the World to be a <hi>Propitiation</hi> and <hi>Attonement</hi> for us <hi>miſerable</hi> Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, who <hi>lay in darkneſs, and in the ſhadow of death,</hi> and he, when he came, to ſhew us that he was the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>genuin</hi> Offspring of ſo <hi>Gracious</hi> a Father, the peculiar Character which is given of him in Scripture is, that <hi>he went about doing Good,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:51617:8"/> and this was the general ſtrain and drift of all his Miracles, he did not ſpend his time in removing of Mountains, or in calling the Sun out of its place, or in any other thing that might create wonder with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any real uſe, but he healed Diſeaſes and he caſt out <hi>Devils,</hi> he reſtored the Lame to their Feet, the Blind to their Sight, the <hi>Paralytick</hi> to their full Strength and Youthful Vigour, his Miracles were exactly like his Doctrine, uſeful and practical, not vain, puffy, <hi>Oſtentatious</hi> things, performed to raiſe Wonder and Aſtoniſhment in the ſpectators, without any real Benefit or Advantage; and when he left the World, he left his <hi>Spirit</hi> behind him with his Diſciples, which was not only a Spirit of <hi>Inſtruction</hi> to guide them into all neceſſary and ſaving Truth, a Spirit of <hi>Courage,</hi> to ſupport them in and under Perſecution, a Spirit of <hi>Power,</hi> to work <hi>Supernatural</hi> and extraordinary effects for the propagation and ſpreading of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> but alſo a Spirit of <hi>Dilection</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> to unite them to one another, and to him their Head; and though this mutual Love and Help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to one another, in our frail condition of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity be a thing that is tied upon us by reaſons of Intereſt, and by principles of Nature, yet in a more peculiar and diſtinguiſhing manner, he made it the Badg and Character of his Diſciples, who were tied and linked more cloſely to one another, by <hi>ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> aſſiſtances of Divine grace, <hi>by the unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace. By this ſhall all Men know,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that ye are my Diſciples, if ye have Love one to another.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:51617:9"/>
            <p> In my Diſcourſe upon which words, I ſhall do theſe Three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall ſhew upon what Reaſons or Principles the Obligation to mutual Charity, and good Will is Founded.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In what Inſtances, and to what Degrees it is to exert it ſelf.</p>
            <p>And Thirdly, What are the great and glorious Advantages that may be reaped from it.</p>
            <p>I begin with the Firſt of theſe, Upon what Reaſons or Principles the Obligation to mutual Charity and good Will is Founded, and they are theſe Three.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Love, Imitation, and Fear of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Example and Command of <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Saviour.</p>
            <p>And Thirdly, The undoubted Intereſt and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of any humane Society whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Love, Imitation, and Fear of God.</p>
            <p>That God is a Being infinitely Lovely, he being the Source and Fountain of all Created perfection, which in himſelf is contained, in an infinitely more <hi>Eminent</hi> and <hi>Tranſcendent</hi> manner, hath been already repreſented; and this lovelineſs of his, for the great Excellence and Perfection of his Nature, is that which is the proper food of a reaſonable mind to Meditate and Exerciſe it ſelf upon, there being nothing elſe that will afford it, either ſo ſuitable or ſo laſting entertainment; and it is likewiſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly the nobleſt object for its Imitation, ſo far as humane frailty is capable of aſpiring to the Glory and Excellence of ſo <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> and bright a Pattern. The <hi>Nature</hi> of God after whoſe <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance,</hi> the Soul of Man was Created, is that, which if it were not for the Cloggs and <hi>Impediments</hi> of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51617:9"/> 
               <hi>Corporeal</hi> part, if we were not dazled by the <hi>Pomps</hi> and Gaieties, carried away Captive by the falſe enticements, and blinded by the ſteams of ſenſe, through which our finer part is weakned and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fracted,</hi> to which we ſhould always naturally deſire to be more cloſely and intimately united; it is that, in the ſtudy and contemplation of which, when our minds are once fitted and prepared for ſo ſublime an Employment, we find the moſt perfect joy and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction; and it is impoſſible for us to think him as we always do, when our thoughts are at leiſure from prejudice and paſſion, and have <hi>emerged</hi> out of the <hi>ſink</hi> of Bodily entertainments, to be ſo very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a Being, to love him according to that love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, with which he then diſplaies and manifeſts his Nature to us, but at the ſame time we muſt be ſtudying to be like him, and to Copy out every day more and more exactly thoſe Beauties in our ſelves, which we Contemplate and Adore in him.</p>
            <p>But if the <hi>Love</hi> of God will not perſwade us to endeavour to be like him, if the <hi>Excellence</hi> of his Nature will not entice and Charme us into an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Imitation of it, let his <hi>Terrours</hi> engage us, let his <hi>Vengeance</hi> affright us, let the conſideration of his <hi>Omnipotence</hi> compel and force us, let <hi>our Fleſh trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for fear of him, and let us be afraid of his judgments,</hi> who expects and requires from us, that as he hath been ſo <hi>Gracious</hi> and <hi>Merciful</hi> towards us, ſo we ſhould be <hi>Kind,</hi> and <hi>Charitable,</hi> and <hi>Helpful</hi> to each other. For God is not only the <hi>Maker,</hi> but he is alſo the great <hi>Guardian</hi> and <hi>Protector</hi> of the World, he is the <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe,</hi> and it his peace that is broken, or in a way of tendency towards a breach and rupture, by all uncharitable habits and diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51617:10"/> of Mind; and therefore it belongs to his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, it is included in the notion of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and is a part of that great task, and buſineſs which he hath impoſed perpetually upon himſelf, for the preſerving by his <hi>Goodneſs</hi> the effects of his <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> and for the Good more eſpecially of the <hi>rational</hi> and <hi>intellectual Creation,</hi> which is more peculiarly the object of his care, not to ſuffer ill tempers, and miſchievous inclinations, <hi>moroſe,</hi> contentious and uncharitable Spirits, ſo far as we Indulge and Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh them in our ſelves, to go unpuniſh'd, either in this World or the other, unleſs by a <hi>timely</hi> and <hi>ſincere</hi> Repentance, we return to the Love of <hi>God,</hi> and of our <hi>Neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Secondly, The ſecond Reaſon or Principle upon which the Obligation to mutual Love is Found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is the <hi>Example</hi> and <hi>Command</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi> which with us, who pretend to embrace his holy Profeſſion, and to have liſted our ſelves, as <hi>true</hi> and <hi>faithful Soldiers</hi> under his <hi>Spiritual Banner,</hi> ought certainly to have very great Authority and Weight.</p>
            <p>For his <hi>Example,</hi> there is nothing more clear, than that his whole Life was nothing elſe, but one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued courſe of Patience, Humility, Meekneſs, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention, Charity, Conſtancy and Equability of Mind, of doing Good to others, and of forgiving Injuries done to himſelf; and for his <hi>Doctrin,</hi> what a mighty ſtreſs he laid upon theſe excellent. Virtues, will appear undeniably by theſe Four particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That he ſums up the <hi>whole Duty</hi> of Man under theſe Two general Heads, the <hi>Love of God,</hi> and <hi>our Neighbour. Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart and with all thy Soul, and with all thy</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:51617:10"/> 
               <hi>Mind; this is the Firſt and Great Commandment, and the Second is like unto it, Thou ſhalt love thy Neigbour as thy ſelf; on theſe Two Commandments hang all the Law and the Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, In ſumming up the Duties of the <hi>Second Table,</hi> he reduces them all under this <hi>ſingle Aphoriſm, Whatſoever ye would that Men ſhould do to you, do ye even ſo to them: For this is the Law and the Prophets:</hi> And under this general Precept there is no queſtion to be made, but <hi>all</hi> the inſtances of <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>good Will</hi> are compriſed, for there is no Man certainly by his own conſent, that would be Injur'd or Defam'd, that would be Kill'd or Murther'd, Wounded or Beaten, that would be Cenſur'd too ſeverely, Watch'd too narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Interpreted too hardly, Puniſht with a rigour al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together diſproportion'd to the guilt and heinouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Crime; there is no Man, if it were at all times perfectly at his own Choice, but he would be well thought of, well ſpoken of, kindly, courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and favourably entreated, and therefore this Precept obliges us not only not to do any injuſtice, but in all caſes whatſoever, to ſhew as much Mercy, as the thing will bear, to ſhew the <hi>ſame</hi> Friendſhip, Gentleneſs and good Nature in <hi>all</hi> the <hi>particular</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances that can happen, which we our ſelves in ſuch circumſtances ſhould <hi>reaſonably</hi> expect, or ſhould be glad to receive, and to interpret all Men, not by <hi>particular</hi> Prejudices and Paſſions of our own, but with an <hi>univerſal</hi> Juſtice, Ingenuity and Candour.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he gives it us in charge in his <hi>Holy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,</hi> not only in <hi>general</hi> terms, to approve our ſelves, as Men of Candid, Courteous, and Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Diſpoſitions, but to be ſo towards our <hi>very Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> and <hi>Perſecutors</hi> themſelves. <hi>If ye love them</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:51617:11"/> 
               <hi>which love you,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>what reward have ye? do not even the Publicans the ſame? And if ye ſalute your Brethren only, what do ye more than others? do not even the Publicans ſo? But I ſay unto you, Love your Enemies, Bleſs them that Curſe you, do good to them that hate you, and pray for them which deſpitefully uſe you and perſecute you.</hi> Which Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of his to his Diſciples, though it were cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly at that time when it was uttered, of greater Extent and Obligation than it is now adays, they being then under great and heavy Perſecution for Righteouſneſs ſake, againſt which there was no <hi>Humane</hi> Remedie but <hi>Patience,</hi> unleſs they would forſake their <hi>Maſter</hi> and their <hi>Profeſſion</hi> together; In which manner we muſt likewiſe interpret thoſe <hi>other</hi> hard Injunctions in this very Chapter, <hi>Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall ſmite thee on thy Right Cheek, turn to him the other alſo; and if any Man will ſue thee at Law and take away thy Coat, let him have thy Cloak alſo; and whoſoever ſhall compel thee to go a Mile, go with him twain;</hi> which are not <hi>now</hi> Precepts of <hi>ſo great</hi> Obligation as they were then, when the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> oppreſt by the <hi>Roman</hi> and the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Power, were in no capacity legally to right them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and therefore it was their beſt and only way to conquer their Enemies, if it might be, by an <hi>obſtinate</hi> Patience, and a firm Reſolution of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going quietly and chearfully the <hi>worſt</hi> they could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict; whereas if theſe Commands were now alſo to be put in practice by <hi>Real</hi> or <hi>Pretended Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> in their converſe with one another, as the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> of that Age were oblig'd to do it, with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to their <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and their <hi>Heathen</hi> Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours; it is manifeſt in this caſe, that the ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51617:11"/> of well meaning Men would but expoſe it ſelf to be the Prey and Spoil of every ſturdy Vagrant; every Midnight Thief, every Covetous, Envious, or Injurious Neighbour, every Lawleſs, Unconſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, or Unreaſonable Perſon; ſo that no <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Society could continue for one Moment, but all would preſently be thrown into the <hi>utmoſt</hi> diſorder and confuſion, which our <hi>Bleſſed Lord,</hi> whoſe <hi>Goſpel</hi> was the <hi>Goſpel of Peace,</hi> as <hi>he himſelf</hi> is ſtil'd the <hi>Prince</hi> of it, cannot be ſuppos'd to have intended; and the ſame was the caſe of that <hi>ſevere Maxim</hi> of his, <hi>It is eaſier for a Camel to go through the Eye of a Needle, than for a Rich Man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven;</hi> which though it were very true in thoſe days, when a Man that embrac'd the profeſſion of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> was either Sequeſtred and Plundered of his Eſtate, or elſe was forc'd to ſell it for the uſe of his poor Brethren, who could not otherwiſe ſubſiſt, ſo that it was <hi>morally</hi> impoſſible for him to keep his <hi>Eſtate</hi> and his <hi>Profeſſion</hi> together; yet <hi>now</hi> the Caſe is clean altered, and it is <hi>now</hi> very poſſible for us <hi>to make to our ſelves Friends of the unrighteous</hi> Mammon, not only by <hi>giving Alms,</hi> to which notwithſtanding we are oblig'd in a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable proportion, but even by <hi>heaping up Riches</hi> for our ſelves, ſo long as they be honeſtly and juſtly gotten, without incurring the danger of Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And after all, in this <hi>hard Chapter</hi> of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon on the Mount, wherein ſo many <hi>difficult</hi> and <hi>ſevere</hi> Leſſons are ſet before the Diſciples, there are theſe <hi>four</hi> things as to the buſineſs of <hi>forgiving Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> which do and will always continue to retain their <hi>firſt</hi> latitude and extent of Truth.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:51617:12"/>
            <p> Firſt, That <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> lays the practice of this duty much more ſtrictly and indiſpenſably upon us than any former Diſpenſation ever did, or than was ever practic'd in the World by any other Sect or Party of Men, as appears undeniably by thoſe words of our Saviour, <hi>If ye love them that love you, what reward have ye? do not even Publicans the ſame? And if ye ſalute your Brethren only, what do ye more than others? do not even the Publicans ſo?</hi> Which is as much as to ſay, that <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> lays <hi>ſtronger</hi> and <hi>more extenſive</hi> Obligations of Charity and Good-will upon us, than ever were ſubmitted to either by the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> or the <hi>Heathen</hi> World, out of both of which at that time in <hi>Judea</hi> the Publicans were indifferently choſen.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we are not to proſecute, and avenge our ſelves of our Enemies without <hi>neceſſity,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our own Life, Liberty, Reputation or Fortune, to vindicate the innocent or afflicted, when it lies in our Power, againſt their unjuſt and unreaſonable Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſours, who are common Enemies to Mankind; or out of Kindneſs and Juſtice to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, which may and do's ſuffer in very many Caſes by the impunity of <hi>private</hi> and <hi>perſonal</hi> Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, As we are not to puniſh <hi>without</hi> neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo we are not willingly to puniſh <hi>beyond</hi> it neither; we are not to exerciſe <hi>Cruelty</hi> but <hi>Juſtice,</hi> not to gratifie an <hi>implacable</hi> and <hi>revengeful</hi> temper, that ſets <hi>no</hi> Bounds or Limits to its Wrath, but we are to mind only the <hi>amendment</hi> of the offending party, or the <hi>due</hi> and <hi>juſt</hi> ſatisfaction of the wrongs that are done us, or the <hi>advantage</hi> which the Publick may and will receive by the neceſſary warning and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51617:12"/> and if the Offence be ſuch as will admit it, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſatisfaction is made us, we are not to decline a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity and Friendſhip with the Offending Party, upon account of <hi>former</hi> grudges or miſunderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, if for the <hi>future</hi> it ſhall appear to be either <hi>prudent</hi> or <hi>ſafe,</hi> of which <hi>we</hi> our ſelves are natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Judges.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, In the midſt of thoſe puniſhments or Forfeitures, which our Adverſary incurs upon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the injuries which either we or the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick have receiv'd from him, we are not to let go our <hi>Chriſtian equability</hi> of temper, we muſt not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer our ſelves to mock at his Calamity, or inſolent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vaunt at his Affliction, or take any other fort of Satisfaction or Complacency in his Puniſhment, than what redounds from the hopes of his amendment by this means, or from the ſenſe of our own preſervation, or the foreſight of a Publick Service, which we may reaſonably expect from the Example. We may Pity him, we may Pray for him, and wiſh, though in vain, that he had not deſerved this Puniſhment, as much as we pleaſe, but we muſt ſtill endeavor to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a gracious and a candid frame of Spirit, we muſt not inſult, we muſt not triumph over him, we muſt not make him the ſubject of our Laughter, or the unſavoury Food of our Revenge. And in theſe Four Senſes which I have now newly mentioned, the Obligation to forgive our Enemies continues ſtill as ſtrong and preſſing upon us, as it was upon the <hi>firſt</hi> Converts in our Saviours time.</p>
            <p>In the Fourth and laſt place, though it were our <hi>Bleſſed Saviours</hi> Expreſs and avow'd Intention to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote and eſtabliſh an univerſal Charity, yet this he preſs'd much more <hi>ſtrongly</hi> and <hi>warmly</hi> upon his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51617:13"/> 
               <hi>Diſciples</hi> with reſpect to <hi>one another,</hi> than in refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their <hi>Enemies,</hi> or to <hi>Strangers</hi> and <hi>Aliens</hi> abroad; that we ſhould Love one another to the <hi>ſame</hi> Degree, to which he Loved us, who <hi>lived</hi> a Life <hi>laden</hi> with Reproach and Scorn, and <hi>died</hi> a <hi>painful</hi> and <hi>ignominious</hi> Death for our ſakes; and this there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he calls a <hi>new Commandment,</hi> a Friendſhip ſo ſtrict, inviolable and Sacred, that it was never heard of in the World before. <hi>A new Commandment I give unto you, that ye Love one another, as I have Loved you, that ye alſo Love one another; by this ſhall all Men know that ye are my Diſciples, if ye have Love one to another.</hi> And how <hi>very great</hi> ſtreſs the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in their Writings lay upon this eminent Gift and Grace of Charity, I need not tell you, but ſhall content my ſelf barely to take notice, Firſt, That St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the <hi>Thirteenth</hi> Chapter of his Firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> imputes ſo very much to this <hi>one</hi> Grace of Charity, that without it he makes all other things, however Pompous or Specious they may ſeem, to ſignifie juſt nothing at all. <hi>Though I ſpeak,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>with the Tongue of Men and Angels, and have not Charity, I am become as ſounding Braſs, or a tinkling Cymbal; and though I have the Gift of Prophecy, and underſtand all Myſteries, and all knowledg, ſo that I could remove Mountains, and have not Charity, I am nothing; and though I beſtow all my Goods to feed the Poor, and though I give my Body to be burned, and have not Charity, it profiteth me nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Whereas moſt other Miraculous Gifts and Graces, were in due time to ceaſe, having done the Errant upon which they were employed, which was to give ſufficient evidence, and ſuch as without willful blindneſs could not be reſiſted to the Truth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51617:13"/> and Divine Authority of our moſt holy Religion; yet <hi>Charity</hi> was ſtill to remain to the very end of the World: So that whereever there is a <hi>true</hi> Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> there muſt be a <hi>charitable Spirit</hi> viſible and reigning in it. <hi>Charity,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>never faileth; but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be Prophecies, they ſhall fail; whether there be Tongues, they ſhall ceaſe; whether there be Knowledg, it ſhall vaniſh away.</hi> And again a little after, <hi>And now abideth Faith, Hope, Charity, theſe three, but the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of theſe is Charity:</hi> As it were to anſwer that Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in St. <hi>John, There are three that bear record in Heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghoſt: and theſe three are one. And there are three that bear witneſs in earth, the ſpirit, and the water, and the blood, and theſe three agree in one.</hi> For in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of St. <hi>Paul, Faith</hi> anſwers to the <hi>Blood;</hi> it is Faith in a <hi>crucified</hi> and <hi>bleeding</hi> Saviour. <hi>Hope</hi> to the <hi>Water</hi> or the <hi>Sacrament of Baptiſm,</hi> in which we make <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of <hi>this Faith,</hi> and of the <hi>Hope</hi> that is in us, which is built upon it. And <hi>Charity,</hi> which is the <hi>beſt</hi> and moſt <hi>peculiar</hi> Gift of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt, that</hi> anſwers to the <hi>Spirit,</hi> which is a Spirit of <hi>univerſal</hi> Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Love, the <hi>eſſential</hi> root, and ſpring, and ſource of Kindneſs, <hi>abſtractum in concreto,</hi> the utmoſt mercy, compaſſion, and good-will, aſſuming a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and breathing forth its likeneſs upon every Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject capable of receiving it. <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> are like <hi>Piſgah</hi> with reſpect to <hi>Canaan,</hi> they afford us a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect</hi> of the Land of Promiſe, but they are not the <hi>Land flowing with milk and honey</hi> themſelves; but <hi>Charity</hi> in its <hi>utmoſt</hi> perfection and extent, is that which in other words we call <hi>Salvation</hi> and <hi>Heaven;</hi> it is the <hi>ſingle</hi> Food, and it affords the <hi>mutual</hi> reliſh and enjoyment of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> and of <hi>the ſpirits</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:51617:14"/> 
               <hi>of juſt men made perfect,</hi> through all the <hi>vaſt</hi> Periods of an <hi>eternal</hi> Duration.</p>
            <p>But wo to us vile wretches and miſerable ſinners, if <hi>without</hi> Charity there be <hi>no true</hi> Church, nor <hi>any true</hi> Diſciple! <hi>O generation of vipers that we are, who ſhall deliver us from the wrath to come?</hi> or will it not be more tolerable for <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> for <hi>Chorazin</hi> and <hi>Bethſaida,</hi> nay, for <hi>Gomorrah</hi> and for <hi>Sodom</hi> too, at the <hi>great</hi> and <hi>dreadful</hi> Day, than for us, who profeſſing <hi>outwardly</hi> the Religion, are yet ſo far removed from the <hi>inward</hi> Spirit of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and, as if we had reaſon to bluſh and be aſhamed of <hi>him</hi> and of his <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which is <hi>the power of God unto ſalvation,</hi> have caſt away the <hi>Badge of Charity,</hi> that Men might not know us to be <hi>his Diſciples.</hi> We are unjuſt in our Dealings, uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in our Cenſures, irreconcileable and implacable in our Animoſities; turbulent and uneaſie in our Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, contentious and litigious in our Converſations, falſe to our Promiſes, treacherous to our Friendſhips, <hi>hypocritical</hi> in our Pretences, and yet we pretend to be <hi>Chriſtians</hi> all this while: Nay, ſo very far have we revolted from the <hi>true Chriſtian Spirit,</hi> ſo far is it now from being thought the <hi>Characteriſtick</hi> and <hi>eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Mark</hi> of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> to be of an humble, meek, and charitable Diſpoſition, that even <hi>Religion</hi> it ſelf, or at leaſt the <hi>vain</hi> pretence and colour of it, is made the fatal <hi>Bone</hi> of Contention, and the <hi>Apple</hi> of Strife. We <hi>quarrel</hi> about that very thing which was intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>unite</hi> us, and which hath made no Promiſes but to Unity and Peace, to the candid, quiet, and ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous frame of Spirit, as if the nature of our Profeſſion were inverted ſince the <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Times, when it was pronounced as a <hi>certain Maxim, If any Man among you ſeem to be Religious, and bridleth not his Tongue,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:51617:14"/> 
               <hi>but deceiveth his own Heart, that Man's Religion is vain;</hi> We miſtake Brawling and Contention for Zeal, and when our Tongues are <hi>ſet on fire of Hell,</hi> we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine them <hi>tipt</hi> and <hi>ſanctified</hi> by a <hi>Coal</hi> from the <hi>Altar;</hi> not but that every Man ought to be <hi>very obſtinate</hi> in what he firmly believes upon his beſt Enquiry to be the very Truth, <hi>every</hi> Man's <hi>own</hi> Conſcience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without queſtion his only rule and meaſure of Action; and to relinquiſh or diſown that of whoſe truth we have all the inward aſſurance our <hi>preſent</hi> light is capable of giving us, is to betray the great Pillar and Principle of Life, by which all Humane Society is ſupported, which is bound up in truth, and conſiſts in the faithfulneſs of its Members to each other: But there may be a <hi>Charity</hi> every whit as <hi>obſtinate</hi> as the moſt <hi>fierce</hi> and moſt <hi>intemperate rage;</hi> and <hi>Humility</hi> will ſtand its ground, and gain upon its Adverſaries by <hi>gentle,</hi> but <hi>reſiſtleſs</hi> Motions, when <hi>Clamour</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Paſſion</hi> ſhall be put to <hi>ſilence,</hi> and will be <hi>aſhamed</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> themſelves: or if there appear reaſon ſufficient to perſuade it, <hi>Humility</hi> can <hi>own</hi> a conqueſt without <hi>ſhame,</hi> and is eaſily induced to change its <hi>miſtaken</hi> Sentiments for the <hi>better,</hi> when <hi>Paſſion,</hi> though it be <hi>inwardly</hi> convinced, yet <hi>bluſhes,</hi> nay <hi>faints</hi> and even <hi>dies</hi> to think of being <hi>reconciled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though I have ſaid, what I believe to be true, That every Man's <hi>private</hi> Conſcience is his only <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi> and <hi>perſonal</hi> meaſure of Action; yet I would not by any means be ſo interpreted, as if I were about to inſinuate, That the <hi>non-execution</hi> of Laws againſt <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious</hi> Diſſenters were a <hi>neceſſary</hi> Branch of that <hi>Charity</hi> to which we are ſo <hi>indiſpenſibly</hi> obliged; no, the Charity lies <hi>manifeſtly</hi> on the <hi>other</hi> ſide, and he that is the <hi>Author</hi> and the <hi>God of Peace,</hi> cannot cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51617:15"/> be diſpleaſed with thoſe <hi>neceſſary</hi> Methods, without which <hi>that</hi> Peace can never be obtained. Since Men are ſo <hi>apt</hi> to quarrel about religious Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, there muſt be a ſtanding Rule in every Nation, to which an <hi>outward</hi> Conformity muſt be exacted. If a Man cannot <hi>comply,</hi> he muſt be content to <hi>ſuffer,</hi> whether he be in the right or wrong: for it is not fit that the Peace of a <hi>Nation</hi> ſhould be put in hazard, and much leſs Embroiled and openly Diſturb'd by the particular Sentiments of <hi>private</hi> Perſons, ſo long as the great Rules of Morality are not invaded. And though no Man ought <hi>ever</hi> to forſake the Truth, or to deny ſo much as the <hi>appearance</hi> of it, ſo long as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the beſt Information he can get, he takes it to be the very <hi>ſubſtance</hi> it ſelf; yet, I preſume, there is no queſtion, but God is leſs diſpleaſed with <hi>Obedience,</hi> which is the <hi>certain</hi> Inſtrument of Peace, though it be founded upon our <hi>mutual</hi> Agreement to ſome Propoſition <hi>ſpeculatively</hi> falſe, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with a <hi>ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Truth <hi>zealouſly</hi> and <hi>contentiouſly</hi> urged againſt the <hi>common</hi> Sentiments, to the diſturbance of the <hi>Publick</hi> Peace and Welfare.</p>
            <p>Much leſs are we to abandon our Senſes, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the common Safety by a too deſtructive Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, for the ſake of thoſe who have neither the <hi>underſtanding</hi> to diſcern what is <hi>fit</hi> in Practice, or <hi>true</hi> in Speculation; nor the <hi>moderation</hi> to ſet <hi>any</hi> bounds to that <hi>innovating</hi> Humour, which will end in <hi>Anarchy</hi> if it be not timely reſtrained, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm <hi>all</hi> Orders and Degrees of Men in a Deluge of <hi>Blood</hi> more fatal than any of thoſe of <hi>Water,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Noah, Deucalion,</hi> or <hi>Ogyges,</hi> which either Scripture or Antiquity have recorded.</p>
            <p>Wherefore we have <hi>no more</hi> liberty left us in this
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51617:15"/> Caſe, but only to inflict <hi>Puniſhments</hi> with a <hi>merciful</hi> Temper, and to <hi>pity</hi> thoſe in the midſt of <hi>legal</hi> Infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, which they do <hi>well</hi> to undergo for <hi>Conſcience ſake,</hi> if they cannot better inform themſelves, whom to be ſure <hi>without,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>with</hi> ſuch Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, we cannot reclaim: But this is a general Rule to be obſerved in this and all other Inſtances whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, That we are never to gratifie <hi>Revenge</hi> under pretence of <hi>Juſtice.</hi> And as we are not upon any terms to <hi>let go</hi> the Reins of Government, and leave the <hi>giddy</hi> Multitude without <hi>any</hi> Curb or Bridle, ſo though we hold them in <hi>never</hi> ſo hard, according to the quality of the Perſons we have to deal with, yet we muſt do it at the ſame time with a generous trouble and uneaſineſs to our ſelves, not with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful, cruel and implacable, but with a pitiful and relenting Hand, and with a compaſſionate ſenſe even of thoſe very Frailties, which we are forced ſo ſharply to chaſtiſe. <hi>Malice, Envy</hi> and <hi>Hatred,</hi> and <hi>all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſs,</hi> are of their <hi>Father the Devil, and his works they do;</hi> they are not <hi>Plants of our heavenly Father's planting,</hi> they are the bane, the poiſon, the canker of the Mind, and like the Tares, the Cockle and the Darnel of the Field, they are not content barely to inſinuate themſelves and grow up among the Wheat, unleſs they alſo <hi>ſtifle</hi> it and <hi>choak</hi> it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they <hi>eat</hi> away its <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>life,</hi> and hinder it from coming to maturity and perfection.</p>
            <p>It is true indeed, there is an <hi>antipathy</hi> and averſion in every wiſe and good Man, while his Mind conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues in its due frame, againſt the very Notion and <hi>Idea</hi> of all kinds of ſin and folly, they appear ſo ugly and ſo deformed to him, they ſtrike ſo ingrateful and ſo harſh a Note upon his Underſtanding; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51617:16"/> it is very <hi>difficult,</hi> and next kin to <hi>impoſſible,</hi> for <hi>frail</hi> and <hi>paſſionate</hi> Creatures as we are, to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>perſonal</hi> hatred from the hatred of the <hi>cauſe;</hi> as when our <hi>Fortunes</hi> or <hi>Good-names</hi> are <hi>violently</hi> and <hi>maliciouſly</hi> invaded, or when our <hi>Lives</hi> are <hi>treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly</hi> and <hi>unjuſtly</hi> aſſaulted; and theſe Paſſions in theſe and the like Caſes, are ſo far <hi>excuſeable</hi> as they are <hi>neceſſary,</hi> or as, it may be, they may be intended by Nature, upon ſuch <hi>important Emergencies</hi> as theſe, for our ſafety, defence and preſervation; but other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe there is no queſtion, but it is the Duty of every good Man, to ſeparate as much as is poſſible, the <hi>Cauſe</hi> from the <hi>Perſon,</hi> and to puniſh the <hi>one</hi> out of no private account, but only for the ſake of the <hi>other,</hi> for our own <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>neceſſary</hi> defence, or for the ſake of Example to the World: But he that encourages and pampers <hi>perſonal</hi> Averſions for the <hi>Perſon</hi>'s ſake, will proceed from one degree of malice to another in purſuance of this <hi>implacable</hi> Diſpoſition, till at length this excellent Gift of Charity ſhall take its flight, and the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> which is a Spirit of <hi>Peace, Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> ſhall refuſe to dwell in <hi>ſuch</hi> a Mind any longer, but ſhall leave it to become the Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>evil Spirits,</hi> and an <hi>Hell</hi> full of <hi>torments</hi> and <hi>inquietudes</hi> to it ſelf. Our <hi>Saviour</hi> will not own ſuch an one to be <hi>his Diſciple;</hi> and there is ſtill the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er danger of his Salvation, if he <hi>profeſs</hi> himſelf out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly to be one of <hi>that number.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this was the Second Reaſon or Principle of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to our mutual love of one another, <hi>viz.</hi> the Example and Command of <hi>Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Saviour.</hi> And certainly if we ſeriouſly conſider, that <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who ſhed his precious Blood for us, did alſo do the ſame for the greateſt and the bittereſt Enemies we have,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51617:16"/> and that at a time when all Mankind were in a ſtate of Enmity to himſelf, nothing can appear more cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal and heinous, than for us to own any Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but thoſe of the higheſt Charity and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will towards <hi>him,</hi> for <hi>whom,</hi> as for <hi>our ſelves,</hi> our <hi>bleſſed Saviour</hi> did not refuſe to Bleed, and who, though really he be <hi>never</hi> ſo bad, may <hi>yet,</hi> upon his hearty and ſincere Repentance, be made partaker of thoſe heavenly Joys, into which we without Charity ſhall never enter.</p>
            <p>But Thirdly and Laſtly, which I ſhall but name. The Third and Laſt Principle of Obligation upon which this great Duty of Charity is founded, is the undoubted Intereſt and Advantage of any Humane Society whatſoever. And certainly, without any painful or elaborate Proof, it is in it ſelf a plain Caſe, That kind and merciful, and charitable Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are the natural and proper Means to preſerve the Publick Order and Eſtabliſhment from falling into ruine and decay; That the contrary Habits of our Minds do break out by degrees into Inteſtine Strife and Hatred, and that they have a fatal tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to the Diſſolution of Kingdoms, the Downfall of Empires, and the Subverſion of every Civil Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, let it be Eſtabliſht never ſo well or wiſely.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariſtophanes, Heſiod, Parmenides,</hi> and others, have delivered it down to us according to ancient Tradition, That Divine Love was the Principle that reduced the <hi>jarring</hi> Elements into this <hi>comely</hi> Frame, which, if it had not been for that, would ſtill have been a diſorderly and confuſed <hi>Chaos,</hi> and without its help and aſſiſtance every moment, would imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately return into it: And I am very ſenſible there is a great deal of truth and weight in what they ſay;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51617:17"/> but yet it is much more true of the <hi>Moral</hi> and <hi>Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual,</hi> than of the <hi>Natural</hi> World, that it is ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Love,</hi> it is ſupported by <hi>Divine Love</hi> from <hi>without</hi> as well as the <hi>other;</hi> but even this would hardly do, as powerful as it is, without a Principle of Love <hi>within</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>I ſhould now, as I promiſed under the Second ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Head, proceed to ſhew in what Inſtances, and to what Degrees this Duty of mutual Kindneſs and Good-will is to exert it ſelf; but this having been already ſufficiently done in my Diſcourſe upon the former Head, as opportunity preſented it ſelf, I may excuſe my ſelf and you from any farther trouble upon that account, and betake my ſelf very briefly to the laſt thing propoſed, which was of the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages redounding from this happy Temper; the <hi>bare Enumeration</hi> of which, ſince it is ſo that my Time will give me leave to do no more, may ſupply the place of an <hi>Exhortation</hi> to it.</p>
            <p>And the Firſt thing I ſhall mention is, That it is in general the moſt <hi>bleſſed</hi> Conſtitution of the Soul of Man, which it is capable of being endued withal. For certainly the <hi>moſt pleaſing</hi> Diſpoſition of the Soul is <hi>Love,</hi> if all the World be not very widely miſtaken in their Senſe and Sentiment of things; and the <hi>moſt eligible</hi> Eſtate which it can wiſh for it ſelf, is to converſe with Objects which it <hi>delights</hi> in; and ſuch this Temper, this ſweet and amiable Habit of the Mind makes every Object more or leſs to be.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is not only a Temper the moſt <hi>bleſſed</hi> in it ſelf, it is not only an imitation of God, who is the beſt Example, as hath been already ſhewn, but it alſo draws down the Influences of his Spirit upon us, which have a <hi>natural</hi> and a <hi>vital congruity</hi> to the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51617:17"/> 
               <hi>charitable</hi> Man. It is effectually at the ſame time a <hi>participation</hi> of the <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> and brings us into an <hi>intimate</hi> and cloſe Communion with the <hi>Supreme</hi> Love, which is glad of every ſuitable occaſion to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe and enlarge it ſelf; and ſo St. <hi>John</hi> at large re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents the matter: <hi>Beloved,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>let us love one another: for love is of God; and every one that loveth, is born of God, and knoweth God. He that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not, knoweth not God, for God is love. No man hath ſeen God at any time. If we love one another, God dwelleth in us, and his love is perfected in us. Hereby we know that we dwell in him, and he in us, becauſe he hath given us of his Spirit;</hi> that is, the Spirit of <hi>Love,</hi> of <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Good-will,</hi> of which he had been ſpeaking before.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, By keeping our Minds cool, and diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged from any turbulent and uneaſie Paſſions. This Temper is perhaps the <hi>beſt natural Judge</hi> of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies in the World; and if it could univerſally obtain, by bringing all things to the <hi>arbitrage</hi> of Reaſon, it would ſoon put an <hi>end</hi> to our <hi>religions</hi> Broils, or at leaſt, it would hinder thoſe <hi>particular</hi> Differences in Opinion from being dangerous to our Peace and Welfare.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, By preſerving our Souls, as it is <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally</hi> diſpoſed to do, in their <hi>true</hi> ſagacity, clearneſs, and <hi>untainted</hi> ſtrength, it prevents thoſe <hi>entangle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> and <hi>perplexities</hi> of thought, which are the cauſe of <hi>moſt</hi> of thoſe Ills to which Mankind is <hi>uſually</hi> expoſed, which run us very frequently upon <hi>deſperate</hi> Courſes, and bring us in the end to <hi>Miſery</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly and Laſtly, It is not only the <hi>beſt prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to the Joys and Glories of <hi>another</hi> World; but
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51617:18"/> when in the <hi>end</hi> of our <hi>Days</hi> we arrive happily at the <hi>end</hi> of our <hi>Hopes,</hi> the <hi>ſalvation of our precious and immortal Souls,</hi> it will be the <hi>greateſt</hi> part of their Fruition and Enjoyment, which conſiſts <hi>mainly,</hi> if not <hi>altogether,</hi> in the love <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Angels,</hi> and of <hi>one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which moſt happy and eternally bleſſed State, God of his infinite Mercy bring us all, by the Merits and Mediation of <hi>his Son,</hi> our <hi>Saviour,</hi> the ever bleſſed <hi>Jeſus.</hi> To whom, with the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> be aſcribed all Glory for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <head>NOTES.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 2. SO <hi>Homer</hi> deſcribes his Poetical <hi>Olympus.]</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame manner <hi>Lucretius</hi> alſo deſcribes thoſe bleſſed and peaceful Places, though he reject them as fabulous at the ſame time; and he takes the Copy of his Deſcription manifeſtly from <hi>Homer.</hi>
            </p>
            <l>Illud item non eſt ut poſſis credere ſedes</l>
            <l>Eſſe Deûm ſanctas in mundi partibus ullis;</l>
            <l>Quas neque concutiunt venti, neque nubila nimbis</l>
            <l>Aſpergunt, neque nix acri concreta pruina</l>
            <l>Cana cadens violat ſemperque innubilus aether</l>
            <l>Integit, &amp; largè diffuſo lumine ridet.</l>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 18. The Publicans were indifferently choſen.] The Adminiſtration of the <hi>Vectigalia,</hi> or <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of the <hi>Roman</hi> State, was primarily in all the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces</hi> in the Hands of the <hi>Romans</hi> themſelves, but under them certain of the Natives of the <hi>reſpective</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:51617:18"/> 
               <hi>Provinces</hi> were employed, as being beſt acquainted with their own Nation, and ſo beſt able to manage the Collection of the Tribute in it. That it was ſo among the <hi>Jews,</hi> is evident by the Inſtances of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, Levi,</hi> and <hi>Zaccheus</hi> in the <hi>Goſpels,</hi> the two firſt of which are mentioned as <hi>Sitting at the Receipt of Cuſtom,</hi> and the laſt is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the chief of the Publicans,</hi> or <hi>Cuſtomers,</hi> that is to ſay among the <hi>Jews.</hi> And from this I will take occaſion to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, as I conceive, a very great Miſtake, which hath hitherto generally obtained among Learned Men, as if <hi>Levi</hi> and <hi>Matthew</hi> were the ſame, only becauſe they are both mentioned by <hi>ſeveral</hi> Evangeliſts as <hi>Sitting at the Receipt of Cuſtom;</hi> and out of this number I do not except <hi>Grotius</hi> himſelf: whereas indeed, they are the Names of <hi>two ſeveral</hi> and <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct</hi> Publicans, as appears by <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 3. where there is diſtinct mention made of <hi>Matthew the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can,</hi> and of <hi>Lebbaeus, whoſe ſurname was</hi> Thaddaeus; which <hi>Lebbaeus,</hi> by the change of the V <hi>Conſonant</hi> into a double B, the <hi>Greeks</hi> having no ſuch Letter as the V <hi>Conſonant</hi> in uſe among them, but always expreſſing it either by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is the ſame with <hi>Levi,</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Chivi</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Emori</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Chitti</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the like; and when it is added <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>whoſe Surname was</hi> Thaddaeus: This <hi>Surname</hi> is to be underſtood of his <hi>Roman</hi> Name, as the other is of his <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> as there is mention made of <hi>John, whoſe Surname was Mark,</hi> Acts 12. 12, 25. and cap. 15. 37. where <hi>John</hi> is <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanan,</hi> the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Name, as <hi>Mark,</hi> is the <hi>Roman.</hi> So that it ſeems it was familiar in thoſe Times, when <hi>Judea</hi> was a <hi>Roman Province,</hi> for Men to have two Names, the one a <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> by which they were better
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51617:19"/> known to their own Countrymen and Kinsfolks, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Name that was given them at their Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion; and the other a <hi>Roman,</hi> or rather in this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance a <hi>Greek,</hi> though at that time very familiar a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Romans,</hi> who called this <hi>Lebbaeus</hi> by the Name of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is a contraction of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> who is by <hi>Claudian</hi> ſomewhere called <hi>Theudoſius,</hi> as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is <hi>Epaphrodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> and many others of the like nature; and of one that was called by this Name expreſs mention is made <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 36. which Name by the <hi>Jews</hi> was cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly called <hi>Thaddai;</hi> as <hi>Doſitheus</hi> they call <hi>Doſthai, Prolomaeus Talmai,</hi> after a barbarous and corrupt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: and indeed all Proper Names of Foreign Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were a very ignorant, unletter'd People, were uſed to corrupt after a ſtrange rate; as <hi>Druſius</hi> conjectures the <hi>Jewiſh Terphon</hi> or <hi>Tarphon,</hi> to have been the ſame with the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Juſtin Martyr.</hi> And I make no queſtion but <hi>Baithos,</hi> who was the fabulous Companion of <hi>Sadoc,</hi> the Founder of the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducean</hi> Sect or Hereſie among the <hi>Jews,</hi> is the ſame with the <hi>Greek</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from whence is the <hi>Latin</hi> Name <hi>Boethius,</hi> ſignifying an <hi>Helper</hi> or <hi>Aſſiſtant.</hi> And they who by St. <hi>Paul</hi> are called <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres,</hi> who are ſaid to have <hi>withſtood Moſes and the Truth,</hi> are by the <hi>Rabbins</hi> corruptly named ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Jonos</hi> and <hi>Jombros,</hi> and at others, <hi>Jochanna</hi> and <hi>Mamre.</hi> And other Inſtances might be given, as well in <hi>Appellative</hi> as <hi>Proper</hi> Names; but theſe are ſufficient for my purpoſe: And, I hope, by this time it is ſufficiently clear, that <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> are <hi>two diſtinct</hi> Perſons, notwithſtanding the general cry of Expoſitors to the contrary, who having taken a falſe ſcent from one another, are never like to find
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51617:19"/> out the truth. <hi>V. Druſ. de trib. Sect. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp; B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xt. Lex. Talmud. in Talmai. pag.</hi> 2598. <hi>&amp; in Jochanna, pag.</hi> 945, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 20. <hi>And though I beſtow all my Goods to feed the Poor, and though I give my Body to be burned.]</hi> Theſe are very proper and genuine Effects of that <hi>Charity</hi> which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> deſcribes, but it ſeems without <hi>Charity</hi> it ſelf, unleſs they proceed out of an <hi>inward</hi> Principle of Love to God on the one hand, and our Neighbour on the other; the bare Acts conſidered by themſelves, will be of no profit or avail to us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 27. <hi>Ariſtophanes, Heſiod, Parmenides,</hi> and others.] The particular Teſtimonies to this purpoſe you may ſee in <hi>Grotius,</hi> in his Learned Notes upon his Book <hi>De V. R. C.</hi> and in Dr. <hi>Cudworth</hi> in his <hi>Intellectual Syſtem;</hi> and thoſe others whom I mean, are <hi>Simmias</hi> the <hi>Rhodian,</hi> and <hi>Orpheus</hi> the Writer of the <hi>Argonautiques,</hi> whoſe Teſtimonies are likewiſe produced by Dr. <hi>C.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
